Huh? It won't open.
なんば
ひびと
(南波日々人)開かねえ…｡
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)レバーを左に回すんだよ｡
Turn the lever left.
レバーって どっちの？
Which lever?
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)うん？１個しかないだろ｡
Hmm? There should be only one.
あれ 本当だ ２つある…｡
Huh? You're right.
There are two.
うわぁ～！
Space Brothers
I can no longer remember
what I tried to forget
When I peeked through the telescope
I realized that our world is tiny
It was a picture of infinity
It's not a one-time thing
We'll walk together
Once we've passed the clouds,
we will hold the world between our fingers
and keep what we lost in mind
#40 Heaven and Hell
(ビー ビー…)
くんれんかん
さいとつにゅう
(通信:訓練官)⦅再突入 失敗！➡
Reentry failed...
えんじょう
オリオンは炎上した｡
２０分後にリトライする⦆
Orion burned up.
We'll try again in twenty minutes.
⦅あ～ またやっちまった⦆
I screwed up again.
What's wrong?
⦅どうなってんだ？前は
もっと上手くできてたのにな⦆
I was doing fine before...
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅ふん…ふぁ～！
あ 終わった？⦆
Oh, are you finished?
⦅また みんなを殺しちゃったよ
ブライアン⦆
I got everyone killed again, Brian...
⦅ん～ やっちゃったか｡
フフッ だが まだ甘いな｡➡
You screwed up?
But that's no big deal.
シュミレーターで死んだ回数なら
俺のほうが上だ⦆
I've logged way more simulator deaths.
ひか
《なんで 俺を自分の控えに
選んだんだ？この人は》
Why did he choose me as his backup?
⦅ヒビトは 自分が死んだら
どうなると思う？⦆
Hibito, what do you think happens after you die?
⦅ん？さあ わかんないけど…⦆
Uh...
I'm not sure...
⦅生まれてない時と
同じだと思う⦆
Wouldn't it be like before I was born?
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅じゃあ
天国とか地獄は？⦆
Then what about heaven and hell?
⦅俺は ないと思うな どっちも⦆
I don't believe in either one.
Why not?
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅なぜ？⦆
⦅だって 天国も地獄も どっちも➡
Because you can only see heaven and hell
生きてる時に見るもんだ⦆
when you're alive.
ダミアン…どこ行った？
Damian...
Where are you?
かんせい
(管制官)こちらヒューストン！
ダミアン ヒビト➡
This is Houston.
Damian, Hibito, come in.
応答してくれ！
じょうきょう
ほうこく
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)状況を 報告しろ｡➡
Give me a status update.
ネットワーク！どうなってる？
NETWORK, what's happening?
(ｾﾐﾛﾝｸﾞ管制官)ダミアンとヒビトの
とだ
通信が途絶えました｡
We've lost contact with Damian and Hibito.
ブランブルック山付近です｡
えいせい
静止通信衛星の➡
Last transmission was near Mons Brandenburger.
The stationary communication satellite may be malfunctioning,
こしょう
故障が考えられますが
可能性としては…｡
but that's unlikely.
キャプコム！ムーンベースに
連絡してみろ｡➡
CAPCOM, open a line to Moonbase.
通じれば 故障じゃないだろ｡
If we can, it's working.
(管制官)情報が途絶える直前に
心拍数が急上昇してる｡
Their heart rates spiked right before we lost contact.
(管制官)どうなってるんだ…｡
What's going on?
This is Houston.
(ｷｬﾌﾟｺﾑ)こちらヒューストン
ムーンベース フレディ➡
Moonbase... Freddy, Buddy.
バディ 応答願う！
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)ダミアンとヒビトにも
呼びかけ続けろ｡
Do you read me?
Keep trying to reach Damian and Hibito.
[TV](ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)こちらムーンベース
ヒューストン どうした？
This is Moonbase.
What's up, Houston?
(ｷｬﾌﾟｺﾑ)ムーンベースには
つながりました｡
I got through to Moonbase.
じょうきょう
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)２人の状況を説明してやれ｡
あと その後の➡
Brief them on the current situation.
指示を 待つように伝えろ｡
Damian.
ダミアン！聞こえるか？
ダミアン！➡
Do you read me?
Damian!
ヒューストン こちらヒビト｡
ヒューストン！
Houston, this is Hibito.
Houston...
えいきゅうかげ
《永久影のあるクレーターにでも
落ちたかな｡通信衛星の電波が➡
Did we fall into a permanently shadowed crater?
Somewhere so deep that we can't receive transmissions?
届かないほど 深い場所に…》
《それか もしかしたら
しょうげき
さっきの衝撃で➡
Or could the crash have damaged our equipment?
通信システムが故障したか…》
The low gravity and regolith saved me back there.
《月の低重力と レゴリスの
クッションに救われた…》
《これが地球だったら
確実に死んでるな…》
If this had happened on Earth,
I'd be dead.
ダミアン！ダミアン！
応答してくれ ダミアン！
Damian! Damian!
Do you read me?
Damian!
ダミアーン‼
《くそっ…叫んだって
聞こえるわけねえよな｡➡
Damn it...
It's not like he can hear me shouting.
わかってるけど…くそ 落ち着け！
自分の声以外 何も➡
I should know that...
Just calm down.
Just like me, Damian can only hear his own voice.
聞こえね～のは
ダミアンも同じだ｡➡
電池残量に問題はない｡酸素も
ﾒｲﾝﾀﾝｸだけで １０時間はもつ｡➡
My battery has plenty of juice left.
And my main oxygen tank has ten hours.
まずは ダミアンを探さね～と…｡
だけど どこへ行きゃいい？》
First, I need to find Damian.
But...
Where do I look?
What if he fell to the bottom?
《はるか下まで 落ちてたら
どうする？この先➡
I have no idea how many kilometers deep this goes.
何キロ下まであるのかも
わからねえぞ》
《くそっ 皮肉だな…ダミアン｡
あんたも見てるか？➡
Damn.
Isn't it ironic, Damian?
Are you seeing this?
やみ
深い闇に落ちたせいで 死ぬほど
星が キレイに見える｡➡
We've fallen into a place so dark,
the stars look incredibly bright.
《めんどくせ～場所だな
ここは》
This place is rough...
《地獄のくせに
天国に見える》
We may be in Hell,
but we can still see Heaven.
《ダミアンもライトを
点けてくれれば➡
It'd be easy to find Damian if he'd turn his light on.
すぐに居場所が
わかるのに…》
《見渡す限り真っ暗ってことは…
ダミアンのライトが故障したか➡
But I'm surrounded by darkness.
Either Damian's light is broken,
あるいは 体を動かせない
状態にあるか…》
or he isn't able to move.
《あるいは…》
Or perhaps...
《こ…この わだちは…
バギーの…》
Th-These tracks...
They're from the buggy!
《いや バギーは真っすぐ
落ちていったはず》
No,
the buggy fell down here.
《なんで横に…》
Why would there be tracks?
あ…ギブソン！
Gibson...
ギブソン こんな所に
いやがったか｡
So this is where you were.
まったく…お前のおかげで
はめ
こんな羽目に｡
Man, you're the reason we're stuck down here.
お前みたいな機械でも ちょっとは
マシにさせてくれるもんだな｡
But I guess a machine
is still better than nothing.
こどく
お前に合うまでの孤独感は
けっこう
結構やばかったよ｡
I was feeling pretty alone before I ran into you.
The probe Gibson disappeared within
たんさき
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)探査機ギブソンが
消えたのが➡
ブランブルック山を中心に
半径３キロメートル以内｡➡
a three-kilometer radius of Mons Blanc.
そして ダミアンとヒビトも
同じ場所で通信が途絶えた｡
And Houston lost contact with Damian and Hibito in the same area.
How much oxygen do they have left?
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)酸素残量は？
２人共 まだ
１０時間は もつだろう｡
They should both have ten hours.
(ｶﾚﾝ)探しに行きましょう！
当然だ｡➡
We need to look for them.
Of course.
だが 全員で行くわけにはいかない
リンダとカレンは残ってくれ｡
But we can't all go.
Linda and Karen will stay here.
でも…もしケガをしてたら
ちりょう
私が治療しないと！
But if they're injured, I'll need to treat them.
確かにそうだが その前に 本当に
２人がケガをしてた場合…｡
You have a point.
But if they're seriously injured,
かつ
２人を担いで
運ぶ力が必要だ｡
we'll need muscle to carry them back.
とにかく ビートルを
きどう
すぐ起動させよう！➡
Anyway, let's start up the Beetle.
From sleep mode, it'll take an hour to get it up and running.
かどう
スリープ状態から稼動までに
６０分は かかるぞ｡
故障してんだか ど～だか
わかんねえな これじゃ｡➡
I can't tell if it's broken down or not...
バッテリーが切れてちゃ
どうしようもねえな ちくしょ！
Nothing I can do if the battery's dead.
Damn.
⦅基本的に月面での船外活動は
２人以上｡主に２人｡➡
EVAs are always conducted with two or more members.
Usually, just two.
They're never done solo.
１人ってのは ありえない｡
何でかわかるな ヒビトよ⦆
Do you know why, Hibito?
⦅そりゃあ まあ…１人だと何か
あった時 助けてもらえないし⦆
Sure...
In case anything happens, someone will be there to help.
Exactly.
⦅その通り｡だが…
人命救助の原則では➡
But the triage rule of thumb is as follows...
第一に こんな文章がある⦆
⦅２人での船外活動中
何らかの事故により➡
If two astronauts conducting an EVA have an accident,
and one astronaut cannot be saved,
仲間の命が助からないと
判断できる時…➡
you must abandon that astronaut, to prioritize your own survival.
これを切り捨て…自分の生還を
第一に考えること｡➡
逆に…自分の命が助からないと
判断できる時➡
On the flip side,
if you realize that you won't make it,
you should prioritize the other astronaut's survival.
もう１人の仲間の生還を
第一に考えること⦆
That's what the manual says...
⦅…って書いてあんだけどね｡
はっきり言って➡
But who can really say
この通りにできるのか
誰にも わからんことだ⦆
what we would do
until the time comes?
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅その時が来るまで⦆
I've got one flare.
《照明弾が一つある｡➡
I could fire it to let Damian know my position.
打ち上げればダミアンに
俺の居場所を教えられるが…➡
もしダミアンに意識がなけりゃ
全く意味がない｡➡
But if he's unconscious, it'd be wasted.
フレディ達が助けに来た所を
見計らって打ち上げる方が➡
It'll be more useful if I wait for Freddy and the others to arrive.
まだ救いがあるか…》
How long will it take them?
《フレディ達が来るまで
どんぐらいだ？え～っと…➡
Let's see...
まず ビートルの準備に６０分｡➡
First, it'll take an hour to prep Beetle.
Beetle's slow, so it'll take eighty minutes to get here.
ビートルはとろいから ここに
着くまで８０分はかかるな｡➡
合わせて２時間２０分｡
つまり 照明弾を打ち上げるのは➡
That makes two hours, twenty minutes.
So I should fire the flare in another two and a half to three hours.
２時間半後から３時間後か…
それまで…》
In the meantime...
《ダミアン‼…無事だったか！》
Damian... You're okay?
またあとで来るよ ギブソン｡
I'll be back, Gibson.
《待ってろ ダミアン！》
Hold on, Damian.
かくにん
発光です！発光を確認！➡
We have a flash...
We have confirmation of a flash!
We have an image from the lunar orbiter.
とら
月周回衛星のカメラが捉えました｡
リッティンガー峡谷です｡
It's over Vallis Rittendinger!
２０秒間の発光なら 間違いなく
ダミアン達の照明弾だ！
If the flash lasted twenty seconds, it's a flare from Damian and Hibito!
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)座標を割り出して
ムーンベースに転送しろ｡
≪了解です！≫
Calculate coordinates, and transmit them to Moonbase.
Roger!
《ダミアン！》
Damian!
《よし！バギーもある》
Good, the buggy's here, too.
ダミアン 大丈夫か？
Damian, you okay?
《だめだ やっぱ通話できない》
No use... We can't communicate.
ちょっと待ってろ ダミアン｡
せつぞく
お互い ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰを接続しよう｡
Hold on, Damian.
Let's use voice writers.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
見えるか？ダミアン｡
Can you see this, Damian?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
ああ…見えるよ｡
Yes, I can...
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ よし 歩けるか？
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ 足をケガした…➡
Good, can you walk?
I injured my leg...
There's no pain, though.
痛みはないが それより
大変なことが…｡
But there's a bigger problem.
My temperature regulation system is busted.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ 体温調節システムが
故障したらしい｡
I'm not getting enough water...
水の循環が
悪くなっているようで…➡
My body is freezing.
体が凍りそうに寒い｡➡
ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝとの話を思い出してたんだ｡
わかるだろ？ヒビト｡➡
I was remembering what Brian told us...
I know you understand, Hibito.
Leave me behind.
俺を置いていってくれ…｡
That's right, Hibito.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
そうだ ヒビト…それでいい…｡
You're doing the right thing...
泣くんだろうな アラン…｡
Alan will probably cry...
Alan...
A little more left, Hibito.
回想 (ｱﾗﾝ)もうちょっと
左いって ヒビト｡➡
Stop, Hibito.
はい ストップ！ヒビト｡➡
Next, pass me the yellow ball...
じゃあ次は その黄色い玉と～
ミノムシ君とって ヒビト｡
And the cocoon.
Cocoon?
ミノムシ君？
あ この変なヤツか｡
Oh, this weird one.
(ｱﾗﾝ)ああもう じっとして！
また重たくなったなあ アラン｡
Come on, stand still.
You've been gaining weight, Alan.
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ妻)ホント アランは
ヒビトにべったりね｡
ああ 兄弟みたいだなあ｡
Alan adores Hibito.
Yeah, they're like brothers.
Hey, Daddy?
ねえ パパ！ツリーに
エイリアンつけてもいい？
Can I hang the alien on the tree?
ああ いいねえ｡つけな｡
何言ってんのよ ダメよ ダメ！
Oh, that's a good idea. Go ahead.
What are you saying?
Absolutely not.
ちぇっ…ダメだって｡
だから言ったろ アラン｡
That's a no go.
I warned you.
But Daddy said it was cool...
だってパパは これカッコイイって
言ってたもん｡➡
あ～ ダースベイベーなら
いいかな？
Is Darth Baby okay?
あ～っ もう アランったら
また悪役をツリーに…｡
Honestly...
Alan's trying to put another villain on the tree.
No, that one's okay.
いや あれはいいんだよ｡
ゆる
あれは許そう｡
Let him hang that one.
これね ヒビト ブライアンの
おっちゃんにもらったやつなんだ｡
You know, Hibito...
This was a gift from Brian.
友達はみんなさ ブライアンは
事故で死んだって言ってるよ｡➡
My friends said that Brian died in an accident.
パラシュートが
開かなかったんだって｡➡
The parachute didn't open.
でもパパは違うって言ってたよ｡
ブライアンのおっちゃんは➡
But that's not what Daddy said.
He said that Brian is still on the moon.
今もまだ月にいるんだってさ｡➡
And if Daddy goes to the moon and doesn't come back,
でね パパが月に行って
もし帰ってこなかったらね➡
that means he's on the moon, too.
そん時は
パパも月にいるんだって｡➡
I'll just have to look at the moon to see him, so there's nothing to worry about.
月を見れば そこにパパがいるんだ
から 何も心配するなってさ｡
でも…そうなったら やだなあ｡
But I don't want that to happen...
現在
《だめだ…バギーも動かねえ》
No good.
The buggy won't move...
《落ちた衝撃でCPUがやられてる｡
バッテリーは問題ないが…➡
The crash knocked out the CPU.
The battery's fine,
しゅうり
修理してる時間はなさそうだ》
but I don't have enough time for repairs.
What are you doing, Hibito?
《何やってんだ？ヒビト…》
《あった！…よし》
Got it...
Good.
《微小隕石も宇宙ゴミも➡
Micrometeorites and space debris don't make it down this far.
あんまり この深さまでは
届かないんだな｡➡
I can see a lot of sharp rocks around.
結構ゴツゴツした岩石が
残ってる…》
If we'd fallen any deeper, we'd have been goners...
《さらに下まで落ちてたら…
危なかった》
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
ヒビト…
何でバギーのバッテリーを？
Hibito, why are you carrying the buggy's battery?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
バギーは すぐには直せねえよ｡
けど これさえあれば➡
It'll take too long to fix.
But this could be our ticket out.
かのうせい
俺らが助かる可能性がある｡➡
このバッテリーで
ギブソンを再起動する｡
I'll use the battery to restart Gibson.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ ギブソン!?
Gibson?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
ああ ちょっと上で待ってるよ｡
あいつは無人探査機だけど➡
Yeah, it's waiting for us up there.
It's just an unmanned probe, but it's big and powerful.
結構デカイし パワーもある｡➡
ダミアン１人ぐらいなら運べるよ｡
It should be able to carry you.
I-I told you to leave me behind, Hibito.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ 言っただろ ヒビト…｡
俺は置いて行けって｡➡
I've determined that I can't make it.
自分の命は助からないと
はんだん
判断したんだ｡➡
ブライアンと話しただろ｡
げんそく
人命救助の原則第一項だ｡
Remember what Brian said about triage?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
結構しゃべれるじゃねえか
ダミアン｡➡
You have enough energy to keep talking, Damian.
原則にあるのは｢仲間より
自分の命を優先しろ｣ってことだ｡➡
He was telling us to prioritize our own lives in this situation.
ただし 仲間を捨ててもいいのは➡
But we only abandon our buddies,
once we've established we can't save them.
｢仲間の命が助からないと
判断できる時｣って話だろ｡➡
俺はさ ダミアン…あんたの命を
助けられると判断してるよ｡➡
Guess what, Damian?
I'm saying that I can save your life.
But we can't wait for Freddy and the others to get here.
そのためには ここでﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ達の助け
を待ってる訳にはいかないよ｡➡
ざっと計算してみたんだ｡
ヤツらが ここに来て➡
I ran the numbers.
It'll take four hours for them to arrive, find us, and pull us out.
俺らを見つけて 上に
引き上げるまで４時間はかかる｡➡
After four hours in the -170 °C dark,
４時間も このマイナス170度の
影にいたらダミアンの命が危ない｡
your life will be in danger.
Th-This is...
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ これは…？
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ 断熱シートだよ｡ﾊﾞｷﾞｰの
ボックスにあった｡➡
An insulation sheet.
It was in the box on the buggy.
If I wrap this around you, it should help preserve your body heat.
巻きつけりゃ 体温低下を
ちょっとは食い止められる｡➡
よし！
Okay.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ ヒビト…俺を抱えて
上に登るなんて無理だ｡
Hibito, you won't be able to climb and carry me.
Come on...
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
おいおい ここは月だよ ダミアン｡
ダミアンの体重と宇宙服の重量➡
We're on the moon, Damian.
Your body and spacesuit
only weigh twenty-five kilograms here.
合わせても
ここじゃ２５キロだ｡➡
２５キロなら
アランを背負うのと大差ねえよ｡
That makes you about as heavy as Alan.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ さあ 行こう｡
Well, let's go.
Tsukuba Space Center
This is all our information?
(星加)情報はこれだけか？
(原田)はい 今のところ｡あとは
ＮＡＳＡの報告待ちです｡
Yes.
We're waiting for an update from NASA.
What about Hibito's parents?
日々人君の両親には？
連絡済みです｡
We've contacted them.
Is that the image of the flare?
えいぞう
(星加)あの映像がそうか？
照明弾の？
Yes, it's over Vallis Rittendinger.
はい｡
リッティンガー峡谷だそうです｡
かぐやⅡのデータを｡
Bring up Kaguya II's data.
はい？
What?
さいしゅ
(星加)かぐやⅡが採取した
未整理の地形データから➡
Use the topographic data Kaguya II obtained
to create a zoomed-in 3D map of the ravine.
この谷をクローズアップした
３Ｄマップを用意してくれ｡
That'll tell us how deep it is.
そうすれば 谷の深さがわかる｡
はい！
Y-Yes, sir!
我々JAXAも できることをやろう｡
JAXA will offer whatever assistance it can.
Wait here for a moment, Damian.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
ちょっと ここで待ってろよ
ダミアン｡
The stones out in the fields
are worn down by their daily existence and disappear
That's their trial
When will we be able to resist fate?
Before you lose all hope
and say that we can't win against gravity
go without stopping
past the goal line
You have such strong convictions
Leave your footprints on this Earth
Maybe their tiny length will cause a miracle in the end
Give us a magnificent jump
Run now and do it
Jump past all you see overhead
This is your stride
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#41 Eighty Minutes to Live
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)＜ヒ…ヒビト…＞
H-Hibito...
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)＜状況が分からない今➡
Given our limited information,
起こりうる最悪のケースを
想定して考えてくれ＞
we must assume a worst case scenario.
＜うっ…何だ？今の衝撃＞
What was that shock wave?
Hibito, let me see your back.
＜ヒ…ヒビト…背中を見せろ｡➡
酸素のメインタンクが
破損してる！＞
Your main oxygen tank has been punctured!
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Eighty Minutes to Live"
＜俺がガキの頃 素直に
月へ行きたいって思えたのは➡
As a kid, I dreamed of going to the moon
アポロの飛行士達が みんな無事に
ちゃんと帰ってきたからだ！＞
because the Apollo astronauts all returned alive!
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
Snapshot from space: "Picture of Mother Earth"
今週の宇宙写真です！
すっげ～！
Awesome!